Thank you so much for your wonderful Dharma talks.
법륜스님, 오늘도 저희들을 부처님의 좋은 법문으로 일깨워 주셔서 정말 감사합니다.
I start my day with practice first thing in the morning.
저는 매일의 수행정진은 새벽에 일어나서 일상을 시작하는 일과로
It is not easy because it is very early,
잠자리 잡혀가며 열심히 잘 해나가고 있는데
but what I find even more difficult is keep writing a practice journal.
의외로 수행 일지를 쓰는 일이 힘이 듭니다.
For practice, I do 108 prostrations with words of prayer,
자신의 기도문대로 108배 참회 정근을 하고
then read the Jungto practice manual.
수행법요집으로 기도하는 매일이
But when I sit down to write a practice journal,
기도시 느끼는 마음 상태가 매번 크게 다를 바 없이 동일하기에
I don’t know what to write
기도 후 수행일지를 마주하고 앉으면
because I feel pretty much the same way every day.
오늘은 또 어떻게 써야할지 막막할 때가 거의 대부분입니다.
Can you please advise me how to write in my practice journal?
이러한 제가 어떻게 수행일지를 써야 할까요?
I wonder if you are little spaced out when you practice,
수행하는 동안에 좀 멍한 상태로 정진을 하고 있지 않나, 이런 생각이 드네요
Maybe you are out of focus when you do prostration.
절 할 때 그냥 멍한 상태로 절을 하는게 아닌가
Let's say your prayer for the practice is “My husband is Buddha”
예를 들면 기도문이 ‘남편은 부처님입니다' 라는 기도문이라고 하면
Or “I will say yes and accept my husband words.”
또는 ‘"예"하고 숙이겠습니다' 라는 기도문이라고 하면,
When you do prostrations repeating 'I will say yes and accepting his words'
절을 하면서 "예"하고 숙이겠습니다. "예"하고 숙이겠습니다.
However, sometimes you were aware you didn't say yes to him
이럴 때 어제 하루의 생활 중에 "예"하고 숙이지 못한 경우가 있다 이거에요
and didn't accept his words.
"아, 내가 그때 ‘예’하고 숙이지 않았구나"
“When my husband said something to me,
남편이 뭐라 그럴 때, "아, 예" 이렇게 대답 안하고
I shouted ‘no’ at him instead of saying ‘yes’."
"아니야!" 이렇게 내가 대답을 했구나
I insisted that I was right.
또 내가 옳다는 것을 내가 세웠구나.
“My husband is Buddha” means
'남편이 부처님입니다.' 이 말이나,
the same as I will say “yes” and yield to him.
'예, 하고 숙이겠습니다' 이 말이나 사실은 뜻이 같습니다.
If your husband were actually Buddha, you would say yes to him, right?
남편이 부처님이라면 무조건 "예" 해야죠?
You wouldn’t say, “No, Buddha, that is not right!” Correct?
부처님한테 "부처님, 그거 아니예요!" 이럴 수는 없잖아, 그죠?
If Buddha says something to you, you would say,
부처님이 말씀하시면, "아, 예."
“Oh, right, right. I will do as you said” without any internal resistance.
"아 예. 그러겠습니다." 이래 되잖아요.
So “My husband is Buddha” means that
‘남편이 부처님입니다' 이말은
you will accept whatever your husband says without any internal resistance.
‘남편의 말에 대해서 내가 조건 없이 받아들인다’ 이런 얘기예요.
You accept the Buddha’s words unconditionally, don’t you?
부처님 말씀을 내가 아무 조건없이 받아들이지요
But just because you accept every word from Buddha
받아 들였다고 해서 내가 부처님 말씀대로
Can you actually do everything he tells you to do? No.
다 행할 수는 있어요, 없어요? 없죠.
When you can’t carry out his teachings,
그러면 행하지 못하면 어떻게 합니까?
What do you do? You repent, right?
'아이고, 부처님 죄송합니다' 하고 우리가 참회 하잖아요, 그죠?
In the same way, even if you accept whatever your husband tells you,
그러니까 남편의 말씀에 내가 "예" 하고 숙이던지
it doesn’t mean you do what he wants every time.
내가 그것을 100프로 다 할 수 있다는 얘기는 아니에요.
You probably can’t do more than what you think you can do.
어쩌면 못하는게 더 많아요.
Then, why should I say 'yes' although I can't complete it
그러면 못하는데 무엇 때문에 ‘예' 합니까?
That’s not the point.
그게 아니에요.
You would say yes because your intention is to accept him at that moment.
그때는 할 마음을 내었기 때문에 ‘예'하는 거예요.
However, you find it is very difficult and not doable.
해보니까 안된단 말이에요.
Then, again, you repent saying 'I am sorry'
그러면 또 "아이고, 죄송합니다" 이렇게 참회를 하면 된단 말이에요.
If you keep practicing it every day, you recognize the moment you say 'no' to him
이렇게 하루하루 해 나가면 이제는 대화하는 중에 ‘여보 그거 아니야!’
and you change your words to 'yes, I will do it' immediately.
이렇게 한 즉시, 금방 ‘아, 아니야, 예 하겠습니다' 이렇게 탁 돌아가진단 말이에요.
Practicing more and more, you can hold your words before speaking out
또 더하게 되면, 아니라는 말이 목구멍에 탁 나오다가,
and remind your prayer words are saying yes, and you will say it to him.
"어, 내 기도문이 숙이는거지" 이러면서 "아, 예. 하겠습니다" 이렇게 된단 말에요.
This is the practice and how it works.
그러면 인제 순간순간 기도가 되는 거예요.
Realizing and repenting what you did is not passing a day
이것을 우리가 하루는 넘기지 않는다는 거예요, 하루는.
How about now?
지금은 어떠냐?
Our habit of saying 'no' continues for 10 years, 20 years or even 30 years.
‘아니야' 이게 10년, 20년, 30년 간단 말이에요.
We continue to blame others for creating problems for us.
‘너 문제야' 이게.
This is why you are feeling so heavy and stifling.
그렇기 때문에 내 가슴이 답답한 거예요.
So, repent for your reply in the past.
그래서 지나간 것은 참회해서 뉘우치고
It became your habit and you keep saying 'no' when the situation happens
지나간 그 습관 때문에 알아도 계속 순간적으로 ‘아니야!’ 이렇게 된단 말이에요.
Don’t be caught up in your thoughts for more than a day.
그러니까 그렇게 되더라도 그런 사로잡힌 상태가 하루는 넘지 않도록 한다.
When you practice in the morning, look back yesterday and tell yourself,
아침에 기도할 때, 어제 하루를 돌아보면서 "아, 그것도 내가 고집했구나"
'I insisted on my opinion, and I missed my words for practice that moment.
"아, 그것도 내가 기도문을 놓쳤구나" 이렇게.
Then, writing your practice journal becomes simple and easy.
그러고 적는 것은 간단하단 말이에요.
"Yesterday, when my husband said something, I said 'no', and
어제 제가 남편이 뭐라고 할 때 내가, '아니야!' 했는데,
I realized that I forgot my prayer words during the practice, 108 prostration.
기도를 하면서 어, 내가 기도문을 놓쳤다는 것을 발견 했다.
The moment I realized it, that's not bothering me and I felt so much better."
그 놓쳤다는 것을 탁 발견하는 순간 답답하던 마음이 시원해졌다'
This is the way you can write the journal.
요렇게 쓰면 된단 말에요.
How can it be the same every day?
그게 어떻게 매일 똑같을 수가 있어요?
I don't understand it.
난 매일 똑같다는 건 이해가 안되요.
It can be the same everyday only if you are focused out and dumb.
매일 똑같을 수 있는 건 멍청할 때만 똑같을 수가 있어요.
If you are dumb and can’t think of anything
멍청해서 아무 생각이 없는 것은
that means, It was stupid yesterday, stupid today, and stupid tomorrow
어제도 멍청했고, 오늘도 멍청했고, 내일도 멍청하고
This is the only case that can be the same every day.
그래서 똑같을 수는 있어요.
Don’t force yourself to come up with something to write in your journal.
그럼 막 억지로 생각을 해내는게 아니에요.
Thoughts arise naturally during bowing if you focus on your words for practice.
그냥 절을 하면서 기도문을 딱 집중하다 보면 기도문과 연관되어져서
This and that kind of thoughts come up
이런저런 생각이 떠오른단 말이에요.
It could be just one thought, could be several thoughts.
뭐 하나 떠오를 수도 있고, 다섯가지 떠오를 수도 있고.
If you really had no thought,
아무것도 설령 안 떠오른다면 어떻게 쓴다?
you can just write down “No thoughts or emotions during my practice today.”
‘오늘은 아무것도 떠오르지 않았다' 이렇게 쓰면 되는 거에요.
What if nothing comes up in your mind tomorrow?
그럼 내일도 아무것도 떠오르지 않으면 어떻게 해요?
Then you can write down '"No thoughts or emotions came up today, again. "
‘오늘도 아무것도 떠오르지 않았다' (웃음)
You may say it’s the same every day.
그러면 어제 것하고 오늘 것이 똑같지 않느냐?
You don’t need to argue about it.
똑같던 안 똑같던 그건 따질 필요가 없어요.
This couldn't be the problem even if it’s same for 100 days,
100일이 똑같다해도 문제가 안되요.
it doesn’t matter if you don’t copy from yesterday one.
어제 것을 보고 빼낀 것이 아니고
If you didn’t have any thoughts or emotions arise,
오늘 기도를 하는 중에 ‘내가 무념무상이었다. 아무런 번뇌가 없었다’
you can just write down “I didn’t have any defilements that came up during my practice.”
그러면 뭐 ‘아무런 번뇌가 없었다' 이렇게 쓰면 되는 거예요.
If you didn’t have anything yesterday or today and won’t have anything tomorrow,
어제도 없었고, 오늘도 없고, 내일도 없고
it might make me say, “Oh, this person must have reached enlightenment”. Who knows? (laughter)
그러면 스님이 딱 읽어보면 ‘아, 이 보살은 이제 공부가 다 됐구나' (웃음)
My point is that you shouldn’t say you didn’t have any defilements
그래서 멍청해서 ‘아무 생각도 없었다'. 이게 아니에요.
because you were spaced out during practice.
정말 자기가 정진하는 중에 ‘아무런 번뇌가 일어나지 않았다’
If you didn’t have any thoughts or emotions arising while you maintained your focus on practice, you can then say I didn’t have any defilements.
그럼 ‘아무런 번뇌도 없었다'
That’s your impression, so you can write down in that way.
그게 소감이잖아. 그렇게 쓰면 되요.
If you have additional moments that you realized or repented about,
근데 그런 뭔가 깨우침이나 뉘우침이 있으면
then you can write about those moments in your practice journal.
‘아. 이런 깨우침이 있었다' 이렇게 쓰면 되요.
You don’t have to try hard intentionally to write down the journal.
의도적으로 쓸려고 용쓸 필요는 없어요.
If you can’t think of anything
‘아무 생각이 안난다' 이거는
that means you are unable to observe the current state of your mind.
자기가 지금 자기 상태가 점검이 안된다는 얘기에요.
In other words, you are just blurred.
멍청하단 얘기예요.
Or you might be Buddha. One of those two.
아니면 부처든지, 둘중에 하나요.
I hope the questioner is Buddha. (Laughter)
아마 이분은 부처님이시겠지.. (웃음)
Thank you.
감사합니다.